welcome back to lumroom
and we have a cheerful wide awake crowd
here
in
diamond mountain well at least one or
two people uh
[Laughter]
so we were at a cute place yesterday
where uh
you know
pablo kirby said you got to help other
people and then what was the answer that
the guy said
no he said i can't even help myself
how can i help other people but that's
true both
and then he convinced us that what we
could help other people because we
have
the equipment
the venice canal
running down the center of your body
right
and then uh he went into he started to
go into an interesting section
that says and not only do you have the
right body
but you have the right
teaching
yeah uh you have the buddhist teaching
and
inside of that teaching you have the
mahayana and inside the mahayana you
have the
adriana yeah diamond mary
and then he said everybody agrees all
the schools agree
remain right they all agree without
distinction between the schools
that you can achieve enlightenment in
one lifetime
and then he
he mentions uh jetson kappa saying you
could achieve it in 12 years and that
you can find in the tantras
that's in the tantras i i have worked on
that question
and
then he says
in special cases three years and three
months okay yesterday i said three years
and i read it more carefully this
morning and it says uh
three years and three months okay so i'm
sorry for the three-month delay
uh
[Music]
many
holy beings of the past in this
tradition have achieved that
right
and i think if you're like me i'll say
uh
yeah but i didn't see anybody achieve
that you know like nobody popped out of
a body
uh into a body of light that i have seen
and then he's like
yeah of course not you know
you wouldn't see it
you have to be close to it to see it
you have to be fairly close to it to see
someone get enlightened
and
uh well i never read about it but that's
the same question you see it's dependent
uh for you to read a book about it
you have to have the seeds to almost be
there
and so you should feel lucky that you
heard someone say it would take you
three years and three months
that's pretty good
you didn't see anybody achieve it
because you don't have those seats but
you do have the seeds
to hear someone say seriously three
years and three months okay
so i have hope okay all right
uh and here's a picture of
[Music]
40.20 yeah happy anniversary
all right this is your three year
anniversary
okay
and you can do it i love it
all right uh
lots of things
they're young
uh
people say this is the last of the the
fifth of the 500s what's that
yeah bad days who said that
yeah in the
diamond cutter sutra lord buddha says we
are in the degenerate times
they call nik do nick nickman means uh
when you have a cup of tea
with was made from leaves of tea and the
junk settles on the bottom that's called
junk on the bottom
so our our days are called junk on the
bottom days we're the junk on the bottom
days it's called nictu
and there are signs of it people don't
live very long there's lots of conflict
in the world
there are certain signs of it
so he says
people say these are the
junk at the bottom of this but
today led
but for each one of us individually for
each one of us individually we have
never seen better times
okay in all the lifetimes you have lived
uh you have never had a better chance
than this you have a body it's still
working pretty much
and uh
you you know they're not blowing up your
house today
and uh so you have a
you have a time you have some space here
okay
and you got diamond mountain
thanks to venoma gelser and venomous
cutting and other hard working
people
like spaghettis and stuff okay
then uh there's two famous meditators
that he mentions milo repo who you
probably heard of
and
and sapa
these are two
tibetan meditators who are famous
because
it is believed that they achieved
enlightenment in this lifetime okay they
went on retreat
at a place
extremely similar to diamond mountain
except much
more difficult
you know lack of grocery stores
and uh colder
and and they achieved it okay and sap
tobe
and zappa's mean name means for fifty
dollars in supply
uh the guy who stays out
in the desert in the hills
okay
that's what his name means
all right his name is like mr diamond
mountain or something and ensa ensem
means
rocky hilly
desert place out in the middle of
nowhere it's his name
okay
their body wasn't any different from our
body
okay they had the same
body we had they had less groceries
so
if they did it we can do it okay
uh
um
this is a weird story okay
means a place a small town in tibet
called
xiao
uh
a lame guy a guy with a bad leg
okay he couldn't walk without a crutch
all right
and uh
means uh
he took a ride on a donkey
the lame
the guy with a bad leg who took a ride
on the donkey okay and the story is
that um this guy with a bad leg
was
sitting on a fence
on a in a corral a donkey girl and the
gate broke open and the donkeys ran out
and one of them hit the
fence and he fell off and he landed on
the donkey
and he had the right of his life you
know
and he was so happy
and
so we're kind of supposed to take the
example of those
mr diamond mountain and other
former milarepa
they're like and we're supposed to think
that we could write on we could in
english new idiom 20 bucks what's the
english idiom
we could ride on their
coattails
the tail of their coat
so in the old days people had long coats
down to their knees and they have piece
of cloth coming down in the back and you
grab it and and you hold on
and
it's like uh milarepa is a donkey
and by accident you fall on top and you
he'll take you to where
if you just follow this guy who did it
before got it
a lame person lucky lame person on a
donkey
is like okay can you can you take the
example of these two people who did it
before okay
and you could get there by the way here
they
no not yet okay
i'm gonna shiver late sir what's up okay
okay please repeat wrong
rim gondola
[Music]
we avoid
meditation on the alarm ram
worse than the plague
how's that
that's another idiom
plague means a disease that killed all
the third half the people in europe
and we avoid somebody says hey you want
to meditate on llama and we're like ah
nah maybe tomorrow
so he
and he and he's saying it in an
interesting way he says
we enjoy reading the deep classics like
mind only
uh we like studying that we like
memorizing tantric rituals
but if somebody says would you like to
spend an hour meditating on
impermanence we're like
maybe tomorrow okay
we tend to favor the more sexy
topics okay
uh love near content
gowani
your tendency to be attracted more
towards the deep philosophy things and
avoid
just a day a short daily meditation on
learning
name a shepherd you don't know the
mahata
yeah you don't know the killing point so
it means you don't know
what's important you you don't know
what's important
you should try to do
alarm and meditation every day and and
you could take
one of those pictures okay there's been
uh
over a thousand pictures already in this
course
and you could take any one and just
meditate on it okay that's what they're
for okay
[Music]
can't say you don't have any all right
uh
here's how we feel about long-range
meditations
the lady
not oh that's the guy on the donkey okay
that's what hap that's us when someone
says let's do alarm ring
like
okay show the last one i think it's kind
of cute
yeah that's the guy with a bad leg who
landed on donkey
okay don't forget you're gonna have a
quiz
on these pictures okay
all right shin tendee double
is an interesting word it means
a basis or a foundation
and it's a code word for body and mind
so uh
when you speak about in the lam rim
and you say you got it then which means
you have a foundation
it means you have an appropriate body
and mind
to become enlightened you have a body
with all the
canals
venice canals grand canal
and uh
and you have a mind that can understand
emptiness so you have a den it's called
a foundation you have a foundation okay
uh chine means later on
i'm not sure you would be able to get
one from
another million years or something i
mean this kind of chance
where you have access to dharma
and access to dharma is a weird thing it
comes and goes right people
we're used to it we live in a country
where you you have free access to dharma
but there's many places where you don't
you're not allowed to study this thing
and um it's it's it's a it's a tragedy
it's available in the world and you're
not allowed to
to read it freely or like that so
you're lucky to have this kind of
attempt to have this kind of body in
mind
means we don't know if
how long it would take us to get this
again okay it's millions of karmas you
would have to do to get this chance
again
and it's not so likely you'd be able to
do that
even even in a body that was created by
those millions of efforts it's kind of
doubtful that you'd be able to
replicate that repeat that okay
then uh
even if you were to find a body in mind
that was working
you know like completely healthy body
and
intelligent mind
uh young good song
[Music]
but then to me
the kind of teaching that you get from
solcapa would be
extremely rare among all the human
beings and and
when i was younger 100 years ago
i saw this kind of sentence like they're
bragging about some kappa and i'd be
like
you know they're just bragging about
their own
the founder of their own tradition but
if once you
get
a lot of background once you read the
classics
especially what we're doing in the mixed
nuts with the great abhidharma and
vanaya masters
once you read the classics
and once you understand them and once
you try to practice them you you you
really understand that some kind of
understood it
you
and i i'm i'm not bragging about it
either i i don't really care i'm not
from tibet
one tibetan tibetan's the same as other
tibetan to me
i don't care who's got this stuff
i'll just go for whichever guy has it
you know
i i mean i don't my parents weren't
copying and i don't have any reason to
be loyal to one tibetan or another
tibetan
but
if you read it and you study it then
you're like oh my god this guy's
this guy's really got it you know and
you you try it you practice some of it
and you have personal
uh
life-changing experiences
frequently you have amazing experiences
that
that no one you ever heard of ever had
and you have them over and over again
and then you're like wow maybe this
guy's
you know he's got a weird name but what
the heck
what's song meaning to ben
onion he was from he was from a little
village called onion fields songkhan
so i mean mr onion field
has got the stuff
there's probably some secret why onion
is important i don't know
i'm not attracted to onions much but
that's some big difference between me
and veronica it's like let's put some
onions on someone you take all of them
i'll sacrifice
so anyways huh
maybe the layers
yeah could very well be i it's something
worth thinking about
uh anyway
to
to encounter those teachings is
extremely rare and by the way all the
mixed nuts books we're working on 27
books at the same time
extraordinary classics
and um
they're all of some compass lineage
and they're all
extremely high quality so you guys are
spoiled you haven't seen the
the other stuff
you know there's 300 000
tibetan scriptures you haven't seen the
you've only seen the cream of the cream
and it's exciting to be in the first
generation
because you get to translate the best
the best books
you get to work on them you get to work
on the
the cream of the cream you know so
that's that's what mixed nuts is all
about
all right
here's the picture for you
uh i don't know this is kind of stupid
one but uh
it's unlikely that you will meet this
person again this is probably the guy
who soldered your house
and you don't get to do it more than
once in your life right i mean normally
so uh
it's like uh
we bought a skyscraper in new york uh
for our diamond business and uh
and it was really difficult
and um
it was very very difficult and
i i was asking
this business partner you know why is it
so difficult to buy a skyscraper
and he said um
think about it
uh you only buy one or two in your life
and you're never gonna
usually when you buy something from
somebody
uh they have to be nice to you so you
come back and buy it again
but you don't buy a skyscraper twice
you know you buy it once so the seller
has no interest in
they don't care if you come back or not
because they know you're not gonna come
back okay
so that's the idea of this picture you
know it's a deal
that was made once
and it's unlikely to be made again okay
anytime soon to to
to get this chance
with this body and mind and this
teaching
and and in this room
we had a
we had a tantric course for
how many years seven years
seven year tantric course i took these
guys to the tantra sub for seven years
uh over ten thousand pages of
translation
and uh i kept telling them
there'll be a day when we're
we won't be together you know we'll all
just
go somewhere else these classes will end
someday
and they're all like no no
no it's gonna go forever
how many are left out of the 80 there's
two here
two three
three
four
three of oh and the other call it four
okay there the 76 are gone okay and
gone to the four wins we see so
uh don't think it's gonna last forever
you know you
it doesn't last forever
this long rim has a
poignant
sentence a sad sentence
where pabonkuran panchay says we will
the people in this audience
will die off one by one
and then the last one will die
and we'll all be gone
the people in this teaching will all be
gone
and it came true
there's nobody left from that audience
that was still like a thousand people
and if you think about it they all
disappeared they're all gone their
country is gone
you know
their religion is almost destroyed
so
you know it's a sad thing it'll happen
okay
therefore
uh so long as you still haven't been
divorced from your body
that's a funny way to say it right
as long as you still haven't been
divorced from your body
uh
you should
think that you would like to have the
bodhichitta which is what is the door to
be a buddha okay so i would like at
least in these classes
before gesla goes to nirvana
i would like to
get the bodhichitta thing down
you know and then i can
i have a good start on becoming a buddha
you know so i'd like to you should kind
of set yourself a
mini goal
of walking between planets once or twice
and meeting all the people in the
universe directly and okay
uh
yeah here's what happens later you got
next picture you guys
i like this picture
he's looking for his next body and mind
because he wasted this one
so
and you know
i'll tell you there's a kind of
there's something about the lum room
if you're lucky enough to sit in the
alarm room before you're old
uh
you don't believe it okay
and i i i started alarm room when i was
49 years ago
and uh
and you sit through it and you and
you're like yeah yeah yeah i know that's
yeah i understand
you know i'm gonna get old yeah okay i
understand
it's a blessing to sit in the alarm room
while you're still young
uh you don't believe it at that time
right stanley
but you
but it it registers on your mind it
stays in your mind and then when you get
older you're like ah goddamn that was
true
oh my gosh
i'm so glad i have that in my head you
know
uh because then you can access what you
learned when you were younger so young
people it i think right such
so
um
this
foreign
uh
i
here
uh
so
i'm
foreign
um
uh
is
maybe
uh
so
to
don't
uh
okay
what
so
here
foreign
you